Okay, so let's talk about two more types
of float.
And you have something called a positive
float and a negative float.
Now let's talk about negative float first.
Negative float can mean one of two things.
Either the project has gone behind a
schedule, and the project going behind
schedule means something has gone wrong
with the critical path.
It's a critical path that has gone behind
schedule.
So negative flow can either mean we've
gone behind schedule.
or time has been taken away.
All right.
So, let's talk about each of these.
So here is the critical path activity that
we've just been talking about.
Activity D here is on the critical path.
Let's say activity D, you know,
it's supposed to finish on day seven.
Let's say it finished on day eight
instead.
It finished on day eight.
That means we have one day of negative.
float.
We have a negative float of one day.
We went behind schedule.
Going behind schedule always refers to the
critical path.
If a non-critical path activity went
behind schedule, not a problem.
If B goes behind schedule
by one day, for example,
that's not going to impact
the schedule whatsoever.
B ends up finishing one day late.
Well, it has a flow of three days.
So going behind schedule always refers to
the critical path.
So D finishes on day 8 instead of day 7,
we finish one day late.
That means we have a negative float of one
day.
Negative float can also mean that time has
been taken away.
So if I go back to the previous slide,
so negative float means project is either
behind schedule or time has been taken
away.
customer took some time away.
So as a simple example,
our project, we have
calculated our critical path of 19 days.
Our project is going to take 19 days.
Let's say halfway through
the project, our customer
comes along and says, hey,
we made a new discovery.
We need to finish by day 17 now.
We need to finish by day 17.
So that means they have taken two days
away from us.
And therefore, we have a negative float of
two days.
Critical path still remains the same.
Critical path does not change.
It's just that we have a negative float of
two days.
Okay, so that's what negative float is.
Either we're behind schedule or time has
been taken away.
Enough for one reason or another.
In the same token, you might come across
this term called a positive float.
And a positive float means we're ahead of
schedule.
Right?
We're ahead of schedule.
Critical path activity has finished early.
So, in our example here, D, D is supposed
to finish on day seven.
Instead of finishing on day seven,
let's say it finished on day six,
one day early.
That means we have a positive float of one
day.
Finish a day early, we have a positive
float of one day.
So we're, you know, one day ahead of
schedule.
So now, this takes us
all the way back right to
the beginning of the
discussion on critical path.
What is critical path?
It's the longest path.
It represents the earliest completion for
the project.
And initially, critical path is going to
have zero float.
However, once you start
executing, you can end
up going ahead of
schedule or behind schedule.
So critical path then, you may end up with
a positive float or a negative float.
So critical path doesn't necessarily
always have just have a zero float.
is the longest path and it's going to have
the shortest float right the smallest
float okay so this discussion when really
was about negative and positive float
right so make sure you understand what
they are negative float behind schedule
all time has been reduced positive float
we're ahead of schedule